Charlie and I were on a plane recently that was hijacked.
With what?
It was hijacked. I'm telling you about our experience on that hijacked plane when the hijackers
picked us out as the two dirty capitalists that they really had to execute.
And, but they were, they were a little abashed about it. They didn't really have anything
against us. So they said that each of us would be given one request before they shot us.
And they turned to Charlie and they said, what would you like as your request?
Charlie said, I would like to give once more my speech on the virtues of Costco.
With illustrations. And the hijacker said, well, that sounds pretty reasonable to me.
And he turned to me and said, and what would you like, Mr. Buffett?
And I said, shoot me first.
Warren Buffett and Charlie Munger this team of the financial world's best together.
Really cute. Today is the financial world's hard day.
Charlie Munger is the world's most successful.
He was 99 years old, high-level to the age of his 100th birthday.
He's only a month. He's the most famous one.
He's Buffett's most powerful.
And he's Costco's best friend.
So he always broadcast his best friend.
He's always the best friend of Costco.
This is why Buffett would say the story of the story.
Let's see Charlie Munger's amazing.
Hello, I'm Bonnie.
Warren Buffett and Charlie Munger
are the most successful business partners.
They are the first company of the world.
The world is the first 10 companies.
Other companies are the first-time product.
But the show is the only company of the world.
The company is the 9th of the world.
Charlie Munger helped Buffett
become the world's most famous person.
He's very clear and clear.
He's not a big fan of the world.
Berkshire every year of the year.
You can see them all together.
They are the same.
Buffett and Charlie Munger
in the company of the world.
Eat this Seas Candy of the
This is the company.
They are 90 years old.
They are still in the company.
The company is still in the company.
The company's most successful.
Charlie Munger didn't appear.
Warren Buffett even brought him
his own company.
Charlie Munger
often in Warren Buffett
he said,
I have nothing to add.
Warren and I both know
some very successful businessmen
who have not one true friend on earth
and rightly so.
That's true.
and that is no way to live a life.
他是 Buffett的左右手
他們投資的這個夥伴關係
可以追溯到好幾十年前
在開始回顧這個傳奇之前
想請你幫忙一件事情
我們頻道的後台數據發現
有一半的影片觀眾
看了影片還沒有訂閱
我們互相答應對方一件事情好嗎
你答應我按下訂閱的按鈕
你沒有辦法想像
這會幫助到我的頻道多少
那我答應你呢
我會一直努力產出更好更快更棒的影片給你
好 開始進入Charlie Munger
精彩的人生故事吧
我會說每次我跟Charlie
我會有至少新的意見
我會有一個新的意見
令我重新重新思考
我們在合作中有很多樂趣
這幾年都很可憐
這很可憐
巴菲特他早期呢
是曾經跟隨著名的這個投資人
葛拉罕的燕地投資理論
也就是說在經濟周期的這個波動裡面呢
有一些公司的股票啊
會像是被別人扔掉的這個燕地一樣
大家看不上眼
但是如果撿起來
還有最後幾口可以抽的價值
1957年巴菲特創了一家投資俱樂部
初期管理的資金30萬美元
當時他不停在股市裡面
找著一些價值被嚴重低估的這個燕地的公司
7年之後呢
巴菲特的管理資金規模已經來到了2200萬美元
但是後來巴菲特被查林蒙格說服
一定要修正這樣的投資策略
所以接著 Penn哥哥
we gave up what I've labeled the cigar butt approach to investing,
which is where you try and find a really kind of pathetic company,
but it sells so cheap that you think there's one good free puff left in it.
And we used to pick up a lot of soggy cigar butts, you know.
I mean, I had a portfolio full of them.
And there were free puffs in them.
I mean, I made money out of that.
But it doesn't work with big money anyway, and we don't find many cigar butts around that we would be attracted to.
But those are the companies that had low returns on equity.
And if you have a business to turning 5 or 6% on equity,
and you hold it for a long time, you are not going to do well.
Charlie Munger後來說說巴菲特換了一種投資策略,
應該要付更高的價格去購買高質量、高品質的公司.
Berkshire 公司交易了大量的C's Candy 糖果公司,
還有可口可樂的股份。
他們甚至在 iPhone 出來很多年之後,
才大量的投資了蘋果的股票。
那也是這些交易,他們賺了非常多的錢。
但是 Buffett 他其實起初是非常反對買這些公司的,
因為當時 Buffett 認為這些公司已經太貴了。
但是 Charlie Munger 就不斷跟巴菲特說,
你要重新思考價值的這個本質。
後來巴菲特他真的被說服了。
從那個時候開始,
巴菲特不再去堅守這個燕地的投資策略。
他把我拒絕了,
從買很便宜的公司,
在很便宜的價格,
知道有些小利益,
我們可以買到很好的商業,
在正確的價格。
它不太有趣,
買一個商業,
在希望這個糞便會被破壞,
之前它破壞。
Charlie Munger 在1948年,
哈佛大學法學院畢業。
剛開始他到加州的法院當了一名律師,
之後他開始投資證券,
擁有他自己一個很成功的投資公司。
同時他也創立了一個很成功的律師事務所,
叫做 Munger Toles。
Charlie Munger跟Warren Buffett,
都在Nebraska的Omaha長大的。
他們兩個在青少年的時候,
都曾經在Buffett的這個,
祖父的雜貨店打工過。
但是當時他們並不是一起工作的,
因為Charlie Munger比Warren Buffett還要達7歲。
他們真正認識是透過朋友介紹的。
當時Warren Buffett20多歲,
Charlie Munger30多歲。
我們在1959年吃飯,
在5分鐘,
Charlie在桌上的笑話,
我做了一樣的事。
他們每個禮拜都會講好幾個小時的電話去討論投資。
Warren Buffett當時鼓勵Munger去放棄法律,
趕快轉而投資吧。
我認識Charlie,
他在教育法,
我告訴他這不是好運動,
但他只是一個蠢業。
所以他...
幸好我聽到。
Munger本來自己就有自己的投資事業了。
他的投資公司表現很好,
從1962年到1975年,
回報是每一年19.8%。
比比較當時的道琼工業指數呢,
平均的回報只有5%。
所以Munger的表現是非常驚人的。
1978年,
Munger正式以副主席的身份加入了這個Berkshire公司。
之後的故事我們都知道了嘛,
他很直白又很誠實的這個投資理念呢,
幫助了Warren Buffett的公司,
一路成長到成為一家好幾兆美元市值的公司。
不過Charlie Munger呢,
不是只有這個Berkshire一家公司喔,
他從1984年到2011年擔任
Westco Financial金融公司的董事長。
後來呢,
Berkshire買下了這個金融公司。
公司被收購之後呢,
Munger又到了一個Daily Journal
去擔任這個董事長。
他之所以深受大家的喜歡,
其中一個原因就是因為他很幽默。
他很幽默。
我妻子增加了她的期望。
Munger的人生理念呢,
認為啊,
錢並不是一切。
雖然他真的很有錢,
而且擁有20億美元的淨資產。
你最終的在做的事,
是要把你從早上的錢拿著小塊錢,
你會更加更加更加更加。
但只要那一切,
是一切失敗的。
人生是更加更加更加更加更加更加責任的財富。
另外還有一個故事可以看得出來,
他對事情的堅持跟想法很有趣。
Munger他是一個很愛捐獻的人。
2013年呢,
他曾經捐錢給Michigan大學1.1億美元去建造學生宿舍。
裡面呢,
可以容納600多個學生是他設計的。
但是這個宿舍呢,
跟其他的宿舍很不一樣啊。
Munger設計的這個宿舍呢,
他堅持啊,
宿舍除了公共的區域之外,
每一間房間都是沒有窗戶的。
因為他覺得每一個人都很喜歡陽光,
如果每一個房間都有陽光的話,
那大家就會待在自己的房間裡面,
不會去公共區域社交去聊天。
那你要睡覺,
你要讀書的時候,
你就回到這個安全舒服的房間裡面。
但是因為只有公共區域有陽光,
所以那就會鼓勵,
甚至是逼迫宿舍的人多多出來房間,
跟大家互動交流。
在他過世的一個月之前呢,
他曾經上節目接受訪問,
當時呢,
他被問到回顧這一生,
他有沒有什麼想要做,
但是還沒有做的事情呢?
接受了 Penn State場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場場
I don't want any, I would have paid any amount to get you 200 pound tuna when I was younger.
I never caught one.
And now I give you the opportunity.
I would just decline going.
I won't even go out after them.
There are things you give up with time.
You're pretty active.
You've got a busy social schedule.
You're on Zoom.
You have breakfasts and lunch.
Well, I like it that way.
Yeah.
That's my idea of a proper old age for me.
And I didn't plan it.
It just happened.
And when it happened, I welcomed it.
I am very good at recognizing unfair advantages.
And I got unfair advantages in old age.
The way I got unfair and I just in non-old age.
And when they came, I just grabbed them.
Boom, boom, boom.
Charlie Munger認為要保持谦虚.
认清有一些事情你不懂.
This is a good thing.
I do.
!
These special features
with Warren Buffett's
more emotional
is perfect
Charlie Munger
took a picture to buy pie
as a example
He said
when you realize
the opportunity
is able to get the opportunity
you should be able to get the opportunity
and get a lot of money
He said
he and Warren Buffett
all have these opportunities
Sure
I basically believe in the
in the soldier on system
Lots of art will come
and you've got to
handle it well by soldiering through
and lots of
a few rare opportunities will come
you've got to learn how to
recognize them when they come
Charlie Munger
說他99歲的時候
幫自己寫的副文
跟他30歲的時候
一模一樣
Charlie, Warren Buffett
told me that a long long time ago
you told him
he should live his life
he should write his obituary
the way he wants it written
and then live his life accordingly
Yeah, sure
I assume you've done the same thing
for yourself
Well
you know, I've written my obituary
the way I've lived my life
and if people want to pay attention
it's all right with me
and if they want to ignore it
that's okay with me too
I'll be dead
but what the difference will make
and so
but I think it's a good
it's not a bad idea
it's important that I
both live in the same house
for decade after decade after decade
after decade
all our friends get rich
and build better
bigger and better houses
and naturally we can
we both consider bigger and better houses
and I had a huge number of children
so it was justifiable even
and I still decided not to live a life
where I look like the Duke of
Wechester or something
and I was going to avoid it
I did it on purpose
Why?
I think it would be good for the children
That it would spoil them?
Yeah, it's...
If you have rich family
you think your duty is to use the wealth
to live grandly
that's what everybody's doing with the money
you will learn from the people who are doing it
Charlie said he was with Warren Buffett
and he didn't expect
to do over 1 million dollars
he didn't expect to do so well
he could do so well
he could do so many thousand dollars
and he could do so many thousand dollars
What happened?
that you didn't anticipate
what led to that success?
Well, we got a little less crazy
than most people
and a little less stupid than most people
and that really helped us
then in addition
we were given as much longer time to run
than most people
because something kept us alive
in our 90's
and it gave us a long track
from our little fiddling start
all the way to the 90's
those are the two things
that really happened
and of course
we wised up over time
we got into better and better companies
and we understood more and more
of the bad things that could happen
even how easy they could creep in
and we avoided them
avoided them even more
as they used to
when we were older
we did when we were young
and it all worked
it all worked
hold on
go with one leg
okay
he's breathing folks
he's breathing
we've got this down to a routine
so I have nothing to add for it
okay